The mission is a man.
Saving Private Ryan is a war, drama, history film directed by Steven Spielberg.
troops storm the beaches of Normandy, three brothers lie dead on the
battlefield, with a fourth trapped behind enemy lines.
Ranger captain John Miller and seven men are tasked with
penetrating German-held territory and bringing the boy home.
Captain Miller, played by Tom Hanks.
Sergeant Horvath, played by Tom Sizemore.
Private Reiben, played by Edward Burns.
Private Jackson, played by Barry Pepper.
Private Mellish, played by Adam Goldberg.
Private Caparzo, played by Vin Diesel.
Saving Private Ryan is a 1998 American epic war film directed by
Steven Spielberg and written by Robert Rodat.
Set in 1944 in Normandy, France, during World War II, it follows a group of soldiers, led by Captain John Miller (Tom Hanks), on a mission to
locate Private James Francis Ryan (Matt Damon) and bring him home safely after his three brothers have been killed in action.
The cast also includes Edward Burns, Tom Sizemore and Jeremy Davies.
Inspired by the books of Stephen E.
Ambrose and accounts of multiple soldiers in a single family, such as the Niland brothers, being killed in
action, Rodat drafted the script, and Paramount Pictures hired him to finish writing it.
The project came to the attention of Hanks and Spielberg, whose involvement, due
to their previous successes, secured the project's development.
Spielberg wanted to make Saving Private Ryan as authentic as possible and hired Frank Darabont and
Scott Frank to do uncredited rewrites based on research and interviews with veterans.
The main cast went through a week-long boot camp to help
them understand the soldier's experience.
Filming took place from June to September 1997, on a $65–70 million
budget, almost entirely on location in England and Ireland.
The opening Omaha Beach battle was the most demanding scene, costing $12 million to
film over a four-week period, and using 1,500 background actors.
Released on July 24, 1998, Saving Private Ryan became one of the year's most successful
films, earning critical acclaim for its graphic portrayal of combat.
WWII veterans described the combat scenes as the most realistic portrayal of their own experiences they
had seen; some said they had been unable to watch it due to their traumatic memories.
The film earned $481.8 million, making it the second-highest-grossing film of 1998, and went on
to win many accolades, including Golden Globe, Academy, BAFTA, and Saturn awards.
Considered one of the greatest war films ever made, Saving Private Ryan's battle-scene filming techniques inspired many subsequent
war, action, and superhero films, and numerous directors have cited Saving Private Ryan as an influence on them.
The picture is credited with having helped to renew interest in WWII at the turn of the
century, inspiring other films, television shows, and video games set during the war.
In 2014, the film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress as "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of dying and death, self
sacrifice, bravery, world war ii, duty.
The tone is emotional.